Dan Rosen

SUMMARY

Technical leader with over 15 years of experience in software engineering, management, training and coaching. Recently transplanted back to Boston, and looking to get back into distributed systems engineering. Above all, I hope to be part of a team that values learning and collaboration, where I can share my knowledge and learn from my teammates.

SKILLS

Scala: Finagle, Akka, Spray, ScalaTest, ScalaCheck, Scalaz, Shapeless, SBT

Java: Guice, Jersey, Jackson, JUnit, Hamcrest, Mockito, Maven

Other languages: C/C++, Haskell, JavaScript

CAREER

Twitter · Tech Lead / Engineering Manager. San Francisco, CA

04.2013 - 10.2015

Managed three teams responsible for Twitter's REST API, including auth, rate-limiting and Scala frameworks Led API monolith decomposition and Mesos migration to improve fault tolerance and developer productivity Implemented API reliability and performance dashboards, used as a template for all new services Fixed sporadic authentication outages by porting from MySQL to "Manhattan" (homegrown Cassandra clone) Developed "Scala School" course and taught to all engineers in new-hire onboarding Provided 1:1 coaching and performance management for 10 engineers ranging from interns to senior staff Mentored three aspiring junior engineers at Hackbright, a local developer bootcamp for women

Marakana · Lead Instructor. San Francisco, CA

11.2011 - 04.2013

Taught and coached over 1,000 engineers in person and via LiveLessons (published by Addison-Wesley)
Researched, developed and delivered new training courses on Scala, Hadoop and JAX-RS
Modernized Marakana's Java courses, including fundamentals, advanced concurrency and web development
Community events: organized the SF Scala meetup, and production of NEScala 2012 conference videos
Business development: spearheaded Scala training partnership with Typesafe (now Lightbend)

Atlassian · Senior Software Engineer. San Francisco, CA

03.2010 - 08.2011

Maintained cross-product plugin SDK and built the "Developer" tab in the Universal Plugin Manager Designed and built plugin usage tracking dashboard for the Atlassian Plugin Exchange (now Marketplace) Wrote plugin development tutorials, documentation, presentations and blogs

Coverity · Senior Software Engineer / Sales Engineer. San Francisco, CA

09.2006 - 04.2009

Developed fast virtual function call resolution and checkers for static defect detection in C++ COM code Designed and delivered Visual Studio and Eclipse IDE plugins, directing a team of offshore developers Planned and executed technical strategy for major customers, closing over \$1.5 million in product sales Led training sessions on software quality, static analysis theory, reporting accuracy and other topics

Cloudmark · Software Engineer. San Francisco, CA

08.2004 - 12.2005

Developed four novel fingerprinting algorithms for email spam and virus detection Wrote i18n/l10n framework from scratch, and internationalized client applications

AOL Music · Technical Lead. San Francisco, CA

02.2003 - 12.2003

Led four-person client development team for AOL Music's internet radio services
Implemented subset of XPath query language to simplify processing of XML metadata snippets

DoCoMo USA Laboratories · Research Engineer (Contract). San Jose, CA

04.2002 - 12.2002

Researched new programming models for multimodal application development and deployment Designed and built prototype system enabling roaming, offline use of multi-platform web applications

Netscape Communications / AOL · Software Engineer. Mountain View, CA

07.2000 - 09.2001

Represented Netscape to the W3C XSL group; contributed to XSL 1.0 and XPath 2.0 standards Contributed to Mozilla's cross-platform UI toolkit and embedding API

EDUCATION

Brown University · Providence, RI

09.1996 - 05.2000

Awarded Bachelor of Arts with Honors in Computer Science, May 2000 Received Senior Prize in Computer Science, funded by the William Gaston Premium Scholarship Received Honors in Computer Science for thesis work, "Topics in Markup and Software Engineering"